A Guide to the Richmond Light Infantry Blues Records, 1794-1933
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Richmond Light Infantry Blues Records, 1794-1933
The Library of Virginia
29873
3.5 cubic feet; 1 box and 11 volumes
Richmond Light Infantry Blues
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Deposited by Mills F. Neal, Richmond, Virginia, 27 January 1941.
Historical Information
The Richmond Light Infantry Blues was founded in 1789 according to its history and tradition and the state of Virginia recognized its formal commissioning date as 10 May 1793. The unit was called into service during Gabriel's Rebellion, the War of 1812, Nat Turner's Insurrection, and John Brown's Harper's Ferry Raid in 1859. The unit served during the Civil War from April 1861 to April 1865, during the Spanish-American War, and the Mexican border police action in 1916. The Blues served as part of the 104th Ammunition Train during World War I. In 1920, the unit was reorganized and incorporated into the National Guard. In 1926, the Blues traveled to Europe with Guard units from Connecticut.
Scope and Content
Records, 1794-1933, of the Richmond Light Infantry Blues consisting of clippings, correspondence, diaries, financial records, histories, indeces, itineraries, lists, magazines, military records, minute books, music, orders, photographs, receipts, reports, scrapbooks, sketches, telegrams and other records detailing the history, service, operations and proceedings of the Richmond Light Infantry Blues, including its service during the Civil War, along the Mexican border, and in World War I. Records detail the Blues' formation as a cavalry unit in 1916 and its reorganization in 1920. Records also detail the unit's trip to Europe in 1926 along with two military units from Connecticut, as well as a visit to Richmond, Virginia, by the Governor's Foot Guard of Connecticut. Records were deposited at the Virginia State Library in 1941 by Major Mills F. Neal and accessioned by the library in 1978, after the organization had disbanded.
Contents List
- Papers, 1877-1896, containing letters, lists, and receipts. (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Newspaper clippings, 1907-1908, from the Richmond Times-Dispatch, the Richmond News-Leader, and the Richmond Evening Journal concerning the visit of the Connecticut Governor's Foot Guard's visit to Richmond. (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Telegrams and correspondence, 1916-1919, relating to the Blues' formation as a cavalry unit. (Box 1, Folder 3)
- History, 1916-1917, of the 1st Squadron Virginia Cavalry (Richmond Light Infantry Blues). (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Movements &c of Company B Blues from Call to Federal Service,June 18 1916, including cover letter from E. Bemiss, April 1921. (Box 1, Folder 5)
- General orders and report, 1916-1917, while stationed at Brownsville, Texas. (Box 1, Folder 6)
- A Brief History of the Lower Rio Grande Valley by Frank Cushman Pierce, 1917. (Box 1, Folder 7)
- History of the 104th Ammunition Train,1918 (2 copies). (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Papers, 1919, concerning reorganization of the Blues. (Box 1, Folder 9)
- The Richmond Blues magazine, February-April 1923 (3 copies of April issue). (Box 1, Folder 10)
- The Richmond Blues magazine, May-August, Fall, and December 1923, (2 copies of July issue). (Box 1, Folder 11)
- The Richmond Blues magazine, mid-winter, March 1924. (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Remember Brownsville by General James Parker, 1926, includes cover letter from Lieutenant Colonel A. Moreno. (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Congressional Record, 13 April 1926, concerning the European trip of the Richmond Light Infantry Blues, the Governor's Foot Guard, and the Putnam Phalanx (the last two units were from Connecticut). (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Itinerary, 1926, for the Blues Foot-Guard Phalanx European trip. (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Foreign press clippings, 1926, about the Blues Foot-Guard Phalanx European trip. (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Diary, 1926, of J. Carter White concerning the Blues' European trip. (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Clippings, 1926, from the New Haven Journal-Courier, the Richmond News-Leader, and the Hartford Times on the return home of the Foot-Guard, Phalanx, and Blues from Europe. (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Photograph, [1926], from the Blues' European tour. (Box 1, Folder 19)
- List of officers of the Blues, [1926]. (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Virginia,[1933], lyrics by Stuart Sheldon, music by James J. Vaughan. (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Richmond Light Infantry Blues record book, 1794-1883, contains history, lists, minutes, resolutions, and rosters. Volume also includes the Richmond Light Infantry Blues Association records, 1877-1879; and loose papers containing lists, sheet music, list of members, Civil War roster, poem for Captain O. Jennings Wise, and color sketch of a Blues uniform (1874). (Volume 1)
- Register of the Richmond Light Infantry Blues, 1843, includes a sketch of a member in uniform, list of members from unit's founding to the Civil War, receipts, and details of unit's Civil War service. (Volume 2)
- Records of the Richmond Jr. Blues, 1856-1859, includes minutes, correspondence and other records. (Volume 3)
- Scrapbook, 1859-1896, includes clippings, certificates, correspondence, menus, programs, and tickets. (Volume 4)
- Minute book, 1866-1876, includes minutes and records, as well as a subscription book for the relief of soldiers wounded at Roanoke Island and a Civil War account. (Volume 5)
- Finance book, 1877, contains accounts for payment of dues and fees. (Volume 6)
- Minute book, 1877-1882, includes clippings, correspondence, and minutes regarding membership and activities. (Volume 7)
- Minute book, 1903-1916, includes minutes and membership information. (Volume 8)
- Scrapbook, 1908, includes articles about the Blues. Also contains 1891 history of the Blues, 1911 dinner program, pamphlets regarding the Blues 1912 trip to New England, War Department orders, 1920, and sketches of a Blues member and a Governor's Foot-Guard member. (Volume 9)
- Scrapbook, 1911, includes clippings about the Blues, invitations and programs. (Volume 10)
- Newspaper index, 1919-1933, to stories about the Blues which appeared in the Richmond Times-Dispatch. (Volume 11)